MICHAEL GILE

CODER, LEADER, STARTUP GUY

Download PDF

mg@mgile.com +1 (713) 263-4840



Profile

Seasoned technology professional, public speaker and expert iOS developer, with a track record of success in most areas of software product development and delivery. Mr. Gile has over 13 years of expertise in software engineering leadership and development roles, including embedded real-time systems, security, mobile application design and development, technical sales and marketing, as well as startup experience.

Skills

Software Development

I am an expert-level iOS (iPhone, iPad, AppleTV) software developer and have published over 10 applications to the Apple App Store. I am additionally fluent in creating web applications with Python/Django and Node.js.

Systems Design

I design and code highlyavailable systems/web applications with Python, Erlang, Node.js. I do this by separating the logical functionality of a system by process separation and tuning of software stacks after aggressive profiling of the minimum viable product, not by creating giant monolithic, multithreaded monsters.

Startup Leadership

Building engineering teams, developing Minimum Viable Products (MVP) with little to no supervision and fundraising/bootstrapping. I am comfortable at all layers of the startup people stack, from individual contributor (software, product management) to CxO. I have participated in multi-million dollar funding rounds as a founder/cofounder and I know what it takes to get a company from \$o and no product to shipping software and making payroll.

	ınical		

The "C's" (C, C++, Objective-C)	iOS (iPhone, iPad, AppleTV2)	Scalable Stack (Tuning, Profiling)
Python	Java (J2ME, Some Android)	Product Management
Server-Side Javascript (Node.is)	CVS / Subversion / Git	

GitHub Projects

atvHelloWorld - Sample project template for building AppleTV2 apps using only XCode 4.

OBD2Kit - Open-Source OBD-2 iOS library to interface to automotive diagnostics systems.

django-linkedinauth - Django middleware to allow seamless authentication using the LinkedIn API.

ChaiOneUtils - iOS library of utilities created at my position at ChaiOne.

ChaiOneUI - iOS library of user interface controls created at my position at ChaiOne.

csv2plist - Simple program to convert CSV to PList format (Apple native list file format, XML or binary).

Node.js Project Code Samples Available Upon Request (Private Repos)

Public Speaking

360iDev, Denver 2011 - AppleTV Apps - Are you ready for the big screen?

TUAW Article - My September 2011 360iDev keynote covered by a prominent Apple blog.

360iDev, San Jose 2010 - iPhone External Accessory Development

<u>ipDevCon, San Diego 2010</u> - iPhone External Accessory Development

360iDev, Denver 2011 - AppleTV Apps: Are you ready for the big screen?

iPhoneDevCamp Houston, Houston 2010

Houston iPhone Developers Meetup - Co-Organizer, published sample code available on meetup.com website.

Selected AppStore Apps FUZZYCar SoftLayer

FUZZYCodes CultureMap

GoPoint (White label FUZZYCar) Weatherford (Enterprise App)

Experience

Wayin

7/2011-Present

Senior Developer

Working on new ways to have fun. iOS, Android, Set-Top Box, Java/MongoDB, Backbone.js

Find out more on 27-September-2011

ChaiOne

2/2011-7/2011

Lead Developer - iOS Team Lead

Lead developer for iPhone, iPad and other mobile applications. Produced a corporate library iPad application for client Weatherford (http://www.weatherford.com), which was showcased at several trade shows. The Weatherford application included a custom PDF viewer, movie playback and TV Out capabilities.

Lead developer for RedFlag Facebook application and service. A Node.js-based service designed to harvest and analyze Facebook profile data to help protect children online. Designed and implemented using the following technologies: Node.js (App Server, Offline Analysis Engine), Riak (Analysis Store), PostgreSQL (Stored Function Development, Schema Design), RabbitMQ

FUZZYLUKE

2007-2011

Founder

Founder of the worlds first open, Internet-scale hosted, branded consumer automotive diagnostic service. FuzzyLuke harvests, analyzes and makes actionable all diagnostic data provided via On-Board Diagnostics (OBD-2), which is standard in all cars manufactured since 1996. Developed all software personally, including iPhone, J2ME and scalable web application (Django with Fabric autodeployment and load-balancing). FuzzyLuke has gone from zero to shipping to enterprise revenue with no outside capital.

Expert-level iOS developer (iPhone, iPad, iPodTouch) and public speaker. (36oiDev, iPhoneDevCamp, iPhoneDevCon) Multiple apps published under personal and professional activities. One of only a handful of Made For iPod/Works With iPhone hardware accessory licensees.

Mezeo

1/2008-7/2009

Senior Software Engineer

Lead developer on the mobile applications team for the Simdesk J2ME client. After Simdesk dissolved and became Mezeo, became sole developer responsible for brand-able iPhone cloud storage application (shipped by SoftLayer) as well as a the first version of the Mezeo Web API(Django/Python) and a Windows native filesystem drop-in similar to DropBox.

Future Point Systems

11/2005-5/2007

Co-Founder, Director of Engineering & Product Strategy

Member of the founding team, worked to create the technology strategy to commercialize a visual

analytics application created by a Department of Energy research lab. Recruited the initial engineering team and led technical presentations to investors, which resulted in raising over \$2 million in 6 months. Successfully closed several large Fortune 50 brand name customers after completing on-site pilot programs.

Wave Systems Sales Engineer

2005-2006

Recruited back to Wave Systems to help evangelize Trusted Computing and to help Trusted Computing Group (TCG) technologies penetrate the enterprise. Active in partner strategy development and sales/marketing activities.

Integral team member in the creation of a Federal Systems group within Wave to work with the US government to create security strategies built upon the Trusted Platform Module (TPM). Worked directly with government agencies, military and federal research laboratories.

Citrix Systems

2004-2005

Lead Security Engineer

Secured legacy applications and conducted research along with the Metaframe Presentations Server and Password Manager teams to secure future generations of Citrix technologies. Worked with components deeply integrated with Microsoft Windows operating systems, necessitating deep understanding of Windows OS subsystems, specifically the winlogon.exe process and the GINA login architecture.

Wave Systems Security Engineer

2000-2004

Designed and co-developed a suite of TCPA (now the Trusted Computing Group) services on top of Trusted Platform Modules (TPM) from multiple vendors. These services included a Privacy CA which issued X.509 certificates per the Identity Credential issuance protocol, as well as a key escrow and maintenance server, among other applications. Represented Wave as the primary voting member for the Conformance and participated in the software stack (TSS) and Infrastructure working groups. Performed as core developer/architect and in numerous customer-facing roles, including technical presales

Worked with product management, software and hardware teams to define engineering and business requirements for a distributed network of hardware security modules controlled through a set of proprietary transaction servers used to permission both the security module and the module applications into the trusted network of devices.

Worked with a small team of security engineers to develop a suite of proprietary communications protocols necessary to securely communicate with and sustain a large deployment of security devices while still maintaining user privacy. These protocols were created using both proprietary and standards-based technologies such as X.509, PKCS (1,5,7,10,11), and standard algorithms (RSA, DES, 3DES, SHA-1).

Wave Systems Software Engineer

2000

Developed the secure kernel and OS libraries that were the foundation of the EMBASSY system. This OS was developed using the ARM SDT for C and assembler and MS VC++ utilizing C/C++ as well as MFC. Also responsible for helping develop and maintain the cryptographic (both software and firmware) libraries that were the basis for all secure transactions (authorization, encryption, etc.). This included RSA, DES, 3DES, SHA-1, MD5, and RC2.

Education

Colorado State University, Pueblo BS CIS